Finding Aid for Alfred Henry Lloyd pamphlets and reprints, 1889-1901 and undated
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alfred Henry Lloyd pamphlets and reprints 1889-1901, undated
Lloyd, Alfred Henry, 1864-1927
6 volumes
[7217] DA 2 L793 P186
Professor of philosophy and dean of the graduate school of University of Michigan. Journal articles and reprints.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was assembled from various sources.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Alfred Henry Lloyd was born January 3, 1864 in Montclair, New Jersey. He received both his B.A. and A.M. degrees from Harvard, then went abroad to study philosophy at Göttingen University in Berlin and Heidelberg University before returning to Harvard for his Ph.D. which he received in 1893. Upon his return from Europe in 1891, Lloyd came to the University of Michigan as an instructor in philosophy. He would remain here his entire career, receiving steady promotions and eventually becoming full professor in 1906. In 1915, Lloyd also became dean of the University's graduate school. Following the death of president Marion L. Burton in 1924, Lloyd was named acting president of the University of Michigan, serving for eight months, February to September 1925.
As a philosopher, Lloyd was the author of several monographs, including Philosophy of History, The Will to Doubt, and Leadership and Progress. He died May 11, 1927.
The collection consists of journal articles on a variety of topics in philosophy, psychology, ethics.
Subjects:
Philosophy.; Psychology.
- Pamphlets and reprints.
  - Vol. I (Volume 1)
    - Evolution Evolved: A Philosophical Criticism. (The Monist, January, 1899 )
    - Time as A Datum of History. (The Philosophical Review, January, 1899 )
    - Epistemology and Physical Science. (The Philosophical Review, July, 1898 )
    - The Stages of Knowledge. (The Psychological Review, March, 1897 )
    - A Psychological Interpretation of Certain Doctrines in Formal Logic. (The Psychological Review, July, 1896 )
    - The Thinker's Idea of God. (The Inlander, February, 1899 )
    - The Reaction. (The Inlander, June, 1895 )
  - Vol II. (Volume 2)
    - Evolution and Immortality. (The Monist, April, 1900 )
    - The Organic Theory of Society: Passing of the Contract Theory. (The American Journal of Sociology, March, 1901 )
    - The Contribution of The Theory of Evolution to The Science of Teaching. (New York Teachers' Monographs, undated )
    - The Social Will. (The American Journal of Sociology, November, 1902 )
    - Physical Psychology. (The Psychological Review, March, 1900 )
    - A Study in the Logic of the Early Greek Philosophy: Pluralism: Empedocles and Democritus. (The Philosophical Review, May, 1901 )
    - A Study in the Logic of the Early Greek Philosophy: Being, Not-being, and Becoming. (The Monist, April, 19020 )
    - Professor Fullerton on 'The Doctrine of Space and Time." (The Psychological Review, March, 1902 )
    - Münsterberg's Grundzüge der Psychologie. (The Psychological Review, May, 1901 )
    - Some Unscientific Reflections Upon Science. (Science, July, 1901 )
    - Scholars of The Cloister: a Defence. (International Journal of Ethics, July, 1902 )
  - Vol. III (Volume 3)
    - History and Materialism. (American Historical Review, July, 1905 )
    - The Philosophy of Plato as a Meditation on Death. (The Harvard Theological Review, July, 1908 )
    - Some Important Situations and Their Attitudes. (The Psychological Review, January, 1907 )
    - The Personal and the Factional in the Life of Society. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology and Scientific Methods June, 1905 )
    - The Poetry of Anaxagoras's Metaphysics. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology and Scientific Methods, February, 1907 )
    - Discussion: Relativity and Reality. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology and Scientific Methods, November, 1904 )
    - The Meaning of \/--l. (The Journal of Philosophy Psychology and Scientific Methods, March, 1908 )
    - The Relation of Righteousness to Brute Facts. (International Journal of Ethics, July, 1908 )
    - Enlightened Action, the True Basis of Mortality. (The Hibbert Journal, July, 1908 )
    - Academic Avocations. (The Inlander, undated )
    - Radical Empiricism and Agnosticism. (Mind: A Quarterly Review of Psychology and Philosophy, undated )
    - The Institution and Some of Its Original Sins. (The American Journal of Sociology, January, 1908 )
    - American Philosophy: the Early Schools. By L. Woodbridge Riley. (From: The American Journal of Theology, July, 1908
      (Book review)
    - La morale rationnelle dans ses relations avec la ehilosophie générale. By Albert Leclere. From: The Journal of Philosophy, 1908 ?)
    - The Eternal Values. By Hugo Münsterberg. (From: The American Journal of Theology, 1909 )
    - Phi Beta Kappa, Alpha of Michigan. (Michigan Alumnus, December, 1907 )
  - Vol. IV (Volume 4)
    - The Passing of The Supernatural, (The Journal of Philosophy, September, 1910 )
    - Ethics and Its History: The Dependence of Ethics on Natural Science, and the Important Difference Between Ethics as Personal Experience and Ethics as a Social Profession. (The American Journal of Sociology, September, 1905 )
    - The Possible Idealism of a Pluralist. (The American Journal of Theology, [1910] )
    - The Logic of Antithesis. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology and Scientific Methods, May, 1911 )
    - The Eternal Values. By Hugo Münsterberg. (From: The American Journal of Theology, 1909 ?)
    - Games of Chance: a Timely Essay on Certain Possibilities of Gallant Living. (The Monist, April, 1911 )
    - The Case of Purpose Against Fate in History. (American Journal of Sociology, January, 1912 )
    - Justice and Happiness. By W. Benett (From: The Journal of Philosophy Psychology and Scientific Methods, 1911 ?)
    - Dualism, Parallelism and Infinitism. (Mind: a Quarterly Review of Psychology and Philosophy, [April, 1911] )
    - The Reign of Science in the History of a Race. (Mind: a Quarterly Review of Psychology and Philosophy, [October, 1912] )
  - Vol. V (Volume 5)
    - Five Great Battles of Civilization. (The American Journal of Sociology, September, 1913 )
    - The High Comedy of Philosophy. (The Monist, October, 1913 )
    - Conformity, Consistency, and Truth: a Sociological Study. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology and Scientific Methods, May, 1913
    - Roger Bacon the Philosopher:, 1214-1294; 1214-1914. (The Open Court, August, 1914 )
    - The Power Behind the Throne. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology and Scientific Methods, December, 1914 )
    - Kant and After Kant. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology and Scientific Methods, July, 1915 )
    - The Duplicity of Democracy: Democratic Equality and the Principle of Relativity. (The American Journal of Sociology, July, 1915 )
    - Incarnation: an Essay in Three Parts. (The American Journal of Theology, January, 1916 )
    - Negation and Direction. (The Philosophical Review, May, 1916 )
    - The Doctrinaire in Time of Crisis. (International Journal of Ethics, July, 1916 )
    - The Formal Bases of Law. By Giorgio del Vecchio. (From: Michigan Law Review, June, 1915 )
    - Self-Realization: an outline of Ethics. By Henry W. Wright. (From: The Journal of Philosophy, 1913 )
    - "Expediency of an Academic Call to Arms: How the University May Accomplish a Valuable Aid to Preparedness Without Providing Military Training". (New York Times, November 24, 1915 )
    - "The Allies as a League to Enforce Peace: the United States and Other Neutrals Urged to Join Them to Establish a New International Order. (New York Times, April 4, 1916 )
  - Vol. VI (Volume 6)
    - Pragmatism and Metaphysics. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology and Scientific Methods, August, 1917 )
    - Psychophysical Parallelism: A Psychological Episode in History. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology & Scientific Methods, October, 1917 ) -
    - Nietzsche, the Thinker: A study. By Wm. Mackintosh Salter. (From: The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology and Scientific Methods, February, 1918 )
    - Moral Values: A study of the Principles of Conduct. By Walter Goodnow Everett. (From: The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology, and Scientific Methods, 1918 ?)
    - Luther and Machiavelli: Kant and Frederick. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology, and Scientific Methods, April, 1919 )
    - The Function of Philosophy in Reconstruction. (The Journal of Philosophy, Psychology and Scientific Methods, September, 1919 )
    - When Gods Are Born. (The International Journal of Ethics, April, 1919 )
    - Ages of Leisure. (The American Journal of Sociology, 1922 )
    - Newspaper Conscience: a Study in Half-Truths. (The American Journal of Sociology, September, 1921 )
    - The Glory of Democracy: Poetry, Comedy and Duty. (The International Journal of Ethics, January, 1918 )
    - Philosophy in The Service of Science, (The Scientific Monthly, May 1920 )
    - The Philosophy of Herbert Spencer, (The Scientific Monthly, August, 1920 )
    - Leadership and Progress. (The International Journal of Ethics, January, 1922 )
    - The Mathematician Pascal, as Philosopher and Saint: 1623-1662. (The Scientific Monthly, February, 1925 )
    - The Time of Day, Part 1. (The Scientific Monthly, [November], 1923 )
    - The Time of Day, Part 2. (The Scientific Monthly, December, 1923 )
    - Science and Mystery. (The Scientific Monthly, June, 1926 )
    - Fellowships and Their Relation to Teaching. (The Educational Review, October, 1921 )
    - Nature and Human Nature: Essays Metaphysical and Historical. By Hartley Burr Alexander. (From: The Journal of Philosophy, 1923 ?)
    - Also the Emergence of Matter. (The Journal of Philosophy, June, 1927 )